Hey guys, welcome back and today we are
going to do distributed tracing. Okay,
so let's start without wasting any time.
So let's first understand the difference
between logs and tracing. So logs
contain plain text or JSON to record
what event happened during the
processing of an API request within the
application. Very important within the
application. So logs is for individual
applications. Let's say that you have
three application app 1, app 2, app 3.
So whenever any request come to a
particular application, this application
maintain its own logs. Okay. So logs is
for application wise. Okay. So we can
record information warning error which
is crucial for our debugging purpose.
tracking errors or failures with the
stack trace and monitoring application
behavior for unusual pattern. That's
what we do, right? We uh if there is any
warning set even if it's not a warning,
we always log the information. For
example, you hit an endpoint slash user.
Okay? And this is your user service.
This is your application. And you hit
this endpoint. So while the business
logic run you might want to print
certain information. So you put log that
hey user created that's all. So this is
an information. So when you see the log
of this API okay for this application
you will see that yes for this API hit a
specific API at a specific point of time
yes user created. So you got certain
information. Okay. So logs can record
API level details such as incoming
request, what request comes, what events
happen while an API request is being
processed in an application and outgoing
response. So it's like when this request
enters, what is the request I received?
What all the events happen which I want
to which I think it's a crucial in the
logs. Okay. So I will uh log that for my
information for my debugging. Okay. And
after that once it is done the output
which I which I'm returning that also I
can log.
Okay. So these all things which
generally we do in logs. So there is
certain limitation that logs do not show
API request end to end journey across
microservices. Let's say app one, app
two, app three. So when you hit an
endpoint slash user. Okay. So it
traveled from app one then app 2 then
app 3 like so it traveled all these
three application. So logs do not show
end to end journey across microser. No.
So it will you have one log for this.
You have a specific log for this. you
have a specific log for this. So when
you are looking at f_sub_1 locks, you
will get information about f_sub_1. When
you are looking at app2 logs, you get
information about app 2. What happened
within an app 2. Similarly, when you
look at the logs of app 3, you will get
to know what happened within app 3. But
end to end, you won't know what
happened. You won't know by looking at
this log itself. F1 log, you don't know
what next happened.
Okay, which service got invoked.
Okay, so how much time other service
took? You don't know. You all have
information about this one particular
service. That's all. End to end
visibility is not there in the logs. If
you are working with this log app 2
logs, you don't know whether app 3 is
got invoked or not, right? How much time
app3 took and all. So that information
is not present inside a law. Only those
information which you have logged that
would be present.
Okay. Automatically it will not tell
that okay this request now moves to app
3. Only if you have put a logger that
hey I am going to invoke app 3 and once
the app 3 gives you the response then
you have print that okay I got a
response from app 3. This much time I
took. This is something which you are
logging. Okay. And that help you for
your information debugging or tracking
purpose. But
how this request
how this request is traveling across
multiple application that logs do not
track.
Okay. And that's where the tracing comes
into the picture. So we'll see that. So
now here if you see that if a request
goes through order service and from
order service go to payment service
each application have their locks
independently. So order service like
okay order created for user ID 55.
Similarly when the request reached to
payment service payment service will
lock something like payment timeout user
ID for 55. So payment timeout happen. So
when you are in the order service you
would be able to see the logs. when you
are in payment service you you would be
able to see this log but there is no
relation between these two you won't be
able to find out hey is this the same
endpoint they both are talking about or
not is this the same API request which I
hit / user is this both log logs talking
about the same thing for the same
request you don't know there is no
relation between these two logs okay so
we cannot easily tie them together like
both these logs belong to a same API
request or not or how long each step
took that also we don't know
that's where distributed tracing comes
into the picture so understand with this
diagram that let's say we have so many
microservices microser one microser 2
microser 3 4 5 like this so when a
particular API request test comes how it
travels
through multiple microservices
in its life cycle.
So we will get to know with the tracing.
So with this one I can with the
distributed tracing with the tracing I
can know that okay when uh this API got
hit these all microservices got involved
and this is the path or sequence in
which this services get invoked and how
much each service took time which
service is the one which caused the
failure or you can say that it's a
bottleneck all you think can identify
with the tracing
Okay, so tracing tracks the path of
request across the microservices
shows highle info like which service
call which service, how much time each
service took, a status quo. Okay,
whether it's a success, failure or
internal validation error, internal
error likewise. But remember that the
tracing does not store detailed logs. So
that's why there is a difference. Log is
like a detailed log detail events what
is happening within an application once
the API request entered the application.
But tracing does not
care about the detail logs. It only care
about like which service called which
service, how much time each service took
and the status code. Okay.
So you can understand with this diagram
right. So it's more mainly focus on the
track of the API request.
So to achieve this to achieve this
tracking
distributed tracing creates trace ID and
span ID. Very important.
Okay. So what is trace ID? Trace ID
connect request across microservices
with one unique ID. So here with this
example, so this API request will get
one trace ID.
Now no matter how many application it
goes to,
they all have one trace ID. So you can
say that one API request, one API
request equals to one trace ID.
Okay? No matter this API request is
traveling through multiple
microservices.
Okay. So we have one trace ID for one
API request.
Then we have a span ID. Each service has
their unique span ID represent
individual part of the work done inside
each service. So now let's say this
request goes first within this microser.
So it create its own span. So it has its
own span ID. It's like how much time
this service took. So then it pass the
request to this next microser. So it
will have its own span ID. Span ID 2,
span ID 1, span ID 3, it's span ID 4. So
the difference is each microservices
doing some unique work that's why they
have also have unique span ID.
Understand with that? Okay.
And trace ID is like used for stitching
them together. So we have different
spans. Spence means like different piece
of work.
So we need something to know that hey
all these spans all these unit of works
are part of the one API request. So
that's why we have only one trace ID. So
it also has trace ID 1. It also has
trace ID 1. It also has trace ID 1. It
also has trace ID 1. So that when we
have different spans we can easily
identify hey these are all belong to one
trace ID itself. Okay so that's the
difference trace ID and span ID with
this two
distributed tracing able to achieve this
tracking behavior.
So consider this with uh another example
I'm just showing you. Let's say this is
API request we hit. It first goes to
service A. From service A let's say it
first call service B then it call
service C and service B internally call
service D like this is the flow of the
API request. So generally this is how
internal information is stored. We will
see that. But let's say service A
service A because this is also doing
some task right. So it will create its
own span ID. So it has span one. Okay.
How much time this service took.
Its parent is null and trace ID is one.
So trace ID is one.
Okay. Then the request goes to service
B. So now it will do certain task its
own. So we need to know right also that
uh so it's span service 2 span two.
So span two and what its parent is span?
Its parent span is s1. So this is its
parent and this is the current span and
also what it is trace ID is T1. So this
is also belongs to a trace one.
Then we have service C. It's it is also
doing some piece of task. So it can also
has to generate its own span span 3. Its
parent span is S1. So it's this is also
its parent and it also belong to a trace
one T1.
Similarly service D it is also doing
some piece of work. When the request
enters here it will creates its own span
span 4 but its parent span is s_2. So
this is its parent and this span is also
a part of trace one. So this is
generally how this information got
stored. So trace ID is common for all
the different spin. And here if you see
each service
generates a unique span for each task.
Okay. So let's say that you have this
service application one. When the
request comes it does certain task and
goes. So this would be like one span
span one start
and as soon as it goes out so here it
does span one start and here it does
span one end. So whatever the time
this span took you get to know that okay
this is the time when request got
entered and this is the time when
request goes out.
Okay. So this much time application one
overall took
internally also let's say you can create
custom span also. Let's say you have
some heavy load. You are doing some DB
operation and you want that hey I want
uh want to track how much uh this DB
operation is taking time. You can create
a new span within this app also. Let's
say spend 2. start. So we will see that
what I'm trying to say you that for each
task we can you can say that wrap it
within a span and span is nothing it is
just track like when it start and spend
two. So how much time this task took
actually
and it's a child of which task. Okay. So
this is the parent and this is the
child. So by default when application
for incoming any request which is coming
to an application that is tracked for
that it creates a new span. Whenever you
create a new thread or you can say that
thread handoff
that also it creates a new span
and whenever like within an app let's
say within an app application and you
have application two whenever you are
trying to invoke an application two that
time also it create a new span. So for
outgoing
outgoing call also it create a span and
let's say application two return the
response. So it will span start span
end. Okay. So by default you can say
that generally these are the events for
which your uh micros service spring boot
microser internally start the spense.
When an request comes within an
application that time whenever you
create a new thread and thread handoff
happen that time it creates a spin and
the outgoing call whenever you are
trying to invoke
the external service that time it
creates a spin.
Okay. So you got it right. So spend
creation means
span you started.
Okay. Whenever a certain event or
certain operation start and whenever
that operation got finished then you
have to end the span. So now you can
track that okay this span is completed
this much time it took.
Okay. So the same example with this
timeline you can understand that when an
API request entered the service A.
So this span is started. Okay. Now this
span is running. While it is running it
is not finished. So let's consider this
as a sync call synchronous call. So
service A is waiting. So it invoke
service B. So service B is span started.
So it is working. While service B is
working, it is not yet finished. Now it
invoke service D. Service D span
started. Now service D finish its work.
Okay. Then request come back to service
B. Service B now finish its work. So its
span got ended.
Then it call reaches to service A. Now
service A let's say call service C. So
it span started. Service C completed
star. So it spans end the control reach
back to service A and then service A
completes its span. So this is span A
and within this span
these all child spans are present. So
now you can get to know that okay when
the request enters here. Okay so this is
the first starting point and this is
where it ultimately end. But you can
also track what all services got
involved. Okay. And how much time each
is service took. Now you get to know
that okay service B is also involved. It
took this much time. And service B
also invoke service D which that which
took this much time.
Okay. So you can clearly see the
hierarchy.
Okay. So this can be done through trace
ID and span ID. Okay. And we also
mention parent span ID. So generally we
call trace ID and span ID. We can
achieve this tracing behavior.
Don't worry if you didn't get the uh
this how this tree is created and all.
We will see an example also. But for now
difference between log and tracing
should be clear. Log is like more
detailed application level events.
Tracing is the track like request goes
from service A to service B who is
parent uh which service took how much
time that's all
also one important thing is that modern
distributed logging system use the trace
ID generated by distributed tracing to
stitch together logs from multiple
microservices that belongs to same API
request. So I gave you example right
previously that if a request goes to
three application
each app maintain their own logs there
is no relation between these three each
maintain their independent logs.
How anyone would able to know that okay
if this is my API request
or I need all the logs which are
involved for all different microservices
which has c perform certain task. Is
there a way? No, but in the modern
distributed logging they use distributed
tracing trace ID. So they all with the
logs they also put trace trace ID 1
trace ID 1 trace ID 1 and for this
request this is a trace ID. So this
trace ID they will use to stitch this
lock together. So when you search with
the trace ID you will get all the locks
involved.
Okay.
So that's what modern distributed
logging system use trace ID to stitch
the logs from multiple microservices
together.
Okay. So if a request goes like from
order service to payment service each
application have the logs independently
but stitch with unique common trace ID.
So let's say order service now have
whenever it put a log it put like also
put a trace ID. Whenever it put a log it
also put a trace ID.
Okay. So we will see that later
distributed logging system.
For today we will focus more on
distributed tracing only.
Okay. So
yes we will see distributed logging
maybe in the next topic but let's today
focus on distributed tracing and its
implementation.
So now let's go one level deep. How is
distributed tracing works? Okay,
let's see the old legacy flow. So in the
old or traditional way we will you we
used to use a spring cloud sleuth
which uses brave library which is
compatible with zipkin backend service.
So what are these terms? So see let's
say you have your application and you
are using this spring cloud sleuth
library.
So now this spring cloud suit youth
library what it does is it takes care of
creation of trace ID. It takes care of
creation of span ID helps in propagation
of trace ID to different micros service.
So all these three things it's done by
this spring cloud slleuth. So creation
of trace ID. So when a request entered
your application
so it sees that okay this is the fresh
request coming so I need to generate a
new
trace ID and it also uh create a span ID
for it now let's say your application is
invoking another application app 2 so it
also takes care of propagating of trace
trace ID so in the header in the payload
code
in header it will add hey this is the
trace ID and I am your parent span
parent span and this is the trace ID so
that app 2 knows that hey I don't have
to create a new trace ID one trace ID is
already going on I need to use this
trace ID and I can create my own span
but my parent is this
okay So in the payload header we are
adding trace ID and parent span ID right
that also propagation is done by spring
cloud slute.
Okay now I told you that every span
is started.
Okay, after that whatever the task you
do was done span need to be end. Okay,
so with that we can say that this span
is completed. Span started span ended.
Now we can get to know that okay this
span took how much time? This operation
took how much time? Okay. So whenever
any span is completed, it is put into
one a synchronous in-memory queue. Okay.
It is done by the spring cloud sleuth
only.
Again only completed span. When I say
completed dispense means span which was
started performed its operation and it
was ended. So span is completed. Okay.
So each span has information that okay
what's the trace ID
what's the span and what its parent span
okay let's say this is the minimum
information it has but it has more
information like what API it invoked
what task it does we can have certain
more information in the span okay so
whenever any span is completed it is put
into this in-memory asyncq
now there is something called zipkin
exporter So spring cloud sleuth is using
certain brave library which is
specifically for zipkin
zipkin back end. So zipkin back end is
what? So here now you have multiple span
span one span two a span three let's say
span 100
now somebody has to stitch it all
together right so who does this there is
certain backends like zipkins z uh
jagger so there and graphna so these are
different backends which has the logic
that once they receive the spans then
they can create a beautiful nice tree
out of it okay let's say okay trace ID
is one T1 this is the trace ID every
each span has information about I told
you trace ID
span ID and also what who is the parent
span so now with that it can create a
tree okay this is the parent span this
is its child this is its child and this
is its child this is the service get
invo so they can create a tree out of
this spense information so Whose does
this back end like zipkin jagger graphna
these are different so spring cloud
sleuth was very very specific it's an
old traditional right it's very very
specific made for zipkin only
so that's why there is something called
zipkin exporter is also used which task
is to read this in-memory queue fetch
out the spans which are completed from
this queue and push it to the zipin back
end and from this zipin back end we can
generate a UI where we can see the
tracing behavior.
Okay. So in the old legacy flow also if
you want some other back end let's say
you don't want zipkin you want jagger or
you want grapha there is certain hack
you have to do it's not very
straightforward because spring cloud
sleuth used brave library which is very
very specific for zipkin so
see
all this span information is in some
format right And let's say
zipin
understand JSON format. I'm just saying
for example some other let's say graph
now understand some XML format and this
is just for example I'm saying so
everyone understand some different
format they have their own protocol. So
brave library was very very specific for
zipkin. So whatever the format it
generate
this span information whatever the
format it is in it is very specific for
zipin only and that is one reason for it
to get deprecated that's my view because
in modern
like there are so many new popular
backend has come Jagger is one of them
graphna is one of them right and with
old spring cloud solut is very difficult
so that's where the modern flow comes
into the picture. So here if you see
overall architecture is same but the
micrometer is the one which has replaced
this spring cloud sleuth.
Now micrometer what it does is it
provide a tracing APIs only. So it's a
interface mostly.
Okay. So this is as an interface. Okay.
You want to create a trace let's say
this is the API /race.
If you want to create a span this you
have to hit this API / span for example.
So this is an this micrometer provides
an API.
Then we have a SDK. So open telemetry
SDK is very popular nowadays. Okay. So
open telemetry why it's very popular.
You can use any SDK or you can say that
any implementation of the micrometer.
Even the brave provides an
implementation for this micrometer APIs.
But again if you use brave you might
have to uh backend might be your zipin.
Okay. But open telemetry is like a
vendor agnostic.
So all whether zipkin jagger graphna
they all understand open telemetry
protocol. So open telemetry protocol
OTLP means like certain format
which it uh generate the span into. So
they all understand that one. So they
have exposed their endpoints that okay
uh we we accept the span let's say
hotel/
span. Zipkin will say that okay if you
have a span into OTLP format protocol
you can use this endpoint I accept it so
today all major backends accept this
protocol OTLP protocol open telemetry
protocol okay and that's what make it
vendor agnostic
okay so you don't need you don't have to
code specific to zipkin or jagger or
graphna all you have to do is you just
change the endpoint and it will connect
it will pass start dumping the spend to
a specific
back end. Okay. So now let's say this is
your spring boot app. In a spring boot
app you need one micros service library
and so this microser library will bring
the APIs then you need its ed SDK. So I
would you can use any any SDK which is
an implementation of micrometer but I
would say that go for open telemetry
because it will we will use OTLP which
is a generic you can change easily
between any back end you want. So you
need one library for open telemetry SDK
which is nothing but a implementation
for micrometer.
So this will take care of creation of
trace ID, creation of span ID and helps
in propagation of trace ID to different
microservices. The same thing what we
have discussed here. But earlier it was
like very specific brave was sleuth has
you can say that hardcoded brave
library. Now it's like uh we have this
interface and whichever you want now you
want open telemetry open telemetry use
it SDK okay now what it will do is it
will dump the span completed span into
this inmemory Q now this span
uh in format would be OTLP protocol you
can say that okay so now there would be
one OTLP exporter. So we need this
library also because this exporter we
can configure that hey after every 5
second you can listen to this queue
after 1 second you can listen to this
queue whatever the span is there
take out and whatever the URL we will
configured here for the back end just
dump there okay we can now configure any
back end whichever we want and from this
one they can now create a UI a specific
UI and we can see that
let's see the implementation it will
become more clear. So first thing is we
need to choose backend service and make
this make the server up. So either you
want to go with Zipkin, Jagger or
Graphna. I am going with Jerger because
this is nowadays more popular. So but
yeah all are good. You can go with
anything whichever you want.
So I am using docker to install and run
it and uh otherwise you can even um
install it and run it. Okay. And uh like
it's a you can search over the internet.
It's a very easy step to install and run
it. So I am just running this command. I
have a docker installed in my system. So
I am just running this command and this
Jagger got its image got installed here
in the docker. So what this command is
doing it's checking if image already
exists locally otherwise it pulls the
image from the docker hub creates a
container run it in the background okay
and these are the export it exposed one
is 16686 this is for UI
okay 4317 this is gRPC endpoint if
you're using that one and 4318 this is
our HTTP endpoint
HTTP OTLP endpoint. OTLP HTTP endpoint.
This is what actually we are interested
in because our OTLP exporter need to
dump
the span which are in which format? OTLP
format. Right? So we need a
port number the URL and port number
where we can push it. So we are running
it local. So it's a local host and port
number is this one 4318.
Okay. And the UI is 16686. So if you
open this after running this you will
see that Jerger UI is up. So here if you
see this is my docker I have a container
Jerger. So I'm just running it starting
it up. Now here if I refresh it
currently service is zero and Jerger UI
is up. So first step is done.
That's the only first step I do. I just
I have a docker. You can install Docker
also. Very easy. And you have to run
this command and Jagger is
like installed in our system up and
running.
Now let's come to our application. Now
step two, we are first setting up first
application. Our main intention is we
have application one which going to call
application two. So first we are doing a
setup of application one.
I told you what all three libraries we
want. First library we want is
micrometer.
It brings an interface API. Second
library we want is this uh open
telemetry SDK which is an implementation
of the micrometer. And the third library
is we want this exporter which push this
to this Jerger back end. So that's three
libraries. So micrometer library comes
with actuator in the spring boot. So
once you add the actuator right
internally
it fetch the micrometer dependency too.
Then we have micrometer tracing bidge
hotel. This is nothing but this will
bring the SDK which is nothing but an
implementation of micrometer APIs.
And the third dependency we have is the
exporter open telemetry exporter
which will push the span completed spend
to the Jagger.
So we have have a proper dependency.
Now in application.properties what I
have added is my where the port number
on where my application is running. I
give my application a name. the name
which I wanted here to also showed up.
Okay. So I give trace app one. Now I am
giving this my
management.tracing.sampling.probability
1.0. So this means that I want 100%
sampling. If if I am sending 100 request
all 100 request I want to trace it. By
default you can check the number. By
default it do I think 25 30% sampling
only not 100%. But if you want to track
all 100% give 1.0 means it will track
each and every request and it will make
sure that it is dumped to the Jagger.
Then management.tracing.end
endpoint you just give the endpoint of
the backend service like zipkin or
jagger or grapha which you want to
connect to. So for jagger it is running
in my local host. So and this port this
is this port is accepting OTLP HTTP so
that I have given if you are using zipin
only you have to change this whatever
the port it accept and wherever it is
running you just need to give it
whatever the endpoint it is accepting
the spense.
So
that's all we need
to enable the distributed tracing in our
application
library
and application.properties.
That's all. Now this will automatically
start generating the spans for incoming
HTTP request.
Okay, incoming whenever the request
enter it will start creating a span for
it and whenever it goes out it will stop
that span
outgoing HTTP request. So you have app
one
app two whenever it at any point of uh
time it invoke the app two at that point
it will create another span
span one end span to start and whenever
it will get the response it will stop
this okay so that also it will take care
of outgoing HTTP request it will create
a span any new thread you will create
that also it will create a span
automatically.
Okay.
So let's add a controller just for
testing. So currently here if you see
for I have only set up one application.
So even when I hit any endpoint on this
app one it should create a span and
trace right even though I am I haven't
set up app two and not invoking it but
even for the f1 whenever any new request
come it should work. That's what I'm
testing. So I have added a rest
controller and exposed one endpoint/
API. Okay. And I'm just uh my main
agenda would be here I will be invoking
app 2. But for now testing purpose I'm
just returning response from f1. That's
all I'm not invoking for now.
Now I hit the endpoint localhost 8080/
ai.
Okay. So response from f1 this got
invoke. Now if you see the Jagger UI
the trace app one come this is the name
which I have given to my application.
Okay. And here if you see the end point
which I hit.
This is the endpoint which I hit.
Okay. And when you drill down this
information you will see something like
this trace ID
is span. So currently only one is span.
Okay this span has trace ID the same
parent one only
is span created. So this is the app one
right when the request enter it created
a span. So span what is the operation /
ai. / API is the one for which this span
is created reference generally within
this reference it contain whether it's a
child of which span so currently it's
not a child it's a parent only so that's
why it is empty start time and total
duration at what time this span got
started and whenever it was finished so
it has like duration how much time
overall this took from start to when it
got ended how much time it took so this
all information is present inside this.
Okay. And we see that when we invoke an
endpoint, information comes in into the
Jagger UI.
Okay. So we are able to set up our
application one properly.
Now application two setup very easy.
Again same thing for application two
also you need micrometer. So it comes
with actuator you need micrometer
interface implementation that is this
SDK hotel bridge and the exporter. So
this three dependency in property file
whatever the port this application is
running the name you want to give. Yes
you want to trace all the requests which
are coming to it and which endpoint it
has to dump this spin. So I have this is
a Jerger endpoint.
So now let's add controller just for
testing. So app 2 is like accepting this
is the API exposed hello from app 2.
Okay. So now we have app 1 and app2
setup. We have app one. We have app 2.
Now app one has to invoke app 2. That's
what I am doing here. Application one
need to invoke application two. So
earlier we had this right here we will
be invoking app to that's what we saw.
So now I am just changing it to this
code. So we have already seen rest
client rest template faint client right.
So I am using restclient. So here if you
see I just use the I so here we have
already seen that I am using restclient
builder and I create a rest line object.
Using that object I am invoking the
localhost 80082 API hello this one API/h
hello and the port which this app2 is
running on 8082.
So I'm just trying to invoke the
endpoint
okay so now what is happening we will
see that before we see the output. So
what we have done is here we have set up
an a f_sub_1
we have set up an app2
now from f_sub_1 we are invoking the
app2 that's what we are doing here okay
now when we are going to invoke the
endpoint of f_sub_1 / ai
what would happen is there this is the
filter server http observation filter.
This filter will get added
automatically.
So we are saying that right hey we added
just pom and application.property and
it's all worked. That's what we did. We
added this pom we added this
application.properties
and we just invoke this / ai and it
worked. How actually this is the filter
server HTTP observation filter which got
added. So you know that filter accept or
intercept each endpoint. So it will
intercept it and it will check. So it
has two case. If you go inside there you
will see that okay it does two thing.
If it does not contain any header trace
parent header then it creates a new
trace and new span
and if it already contain a trace parent
it will use the same trace only but
create only new span that's all
okay so that's what for every operation
is new span has to be created but
whether it's a new trace or not that it
has this logic like in a header it check
trace parent header.
Now similarly when app one try to invoke
the app 2 at this when it will invoke
the app to write outgoing call. So there
is an interceptor got added too.
Okay this interceptor
adds a propagation header. So in the
header also it add trace parent header
that what's the trace id what's the span
id parent span id. So who who does this
interceptor? So these two things are
important. When a request enters an
application, here comes a filter. This
is the filter. And whenever the request
goes out interceptors, it adds so that
it can append the header. Whatever the
uh application it is another microser it
is calling. So it should append the
header also.
So here if you see now with this
outgoing call it will start propagating
trace ID and spend to other
microservices like this. So header name
is this trace parent and then it will
append the trace ID hyphen span ID. This
is your so when app 2 receive the call
in the header it will have this info.
What's the trace ID and what is the
span? So this will become the parent of
this app 2.
Okay,
one thing before even I show you the
demo
for the rest client here if you see we
have already seen rest line rest
template fang client so I'm not going in
in depth of it so you remember that we
can create an object of rest client in
two ways okay so one is through builder
like uh here we are builder.build
another is through directly
restline.create.
So with only builder it able to add an
interceptor
with create it do not add an
interceptor. So let's say if you are
creating a rest client object through
this create
and then invoke it then when you hit it
you will see that hey it created a span
but it has trace ID 1 it has trace ID 2
why because this interceptor is not
involved the main task of so understand
with this f_sub_1
f_sub_2
what would happen when f_sub_1 is
invoking app 2. So it has a span one
trace one. Now it is invoking it. Now
when it invoked it, it also has tracing
distributed tracing dependency and
everything. Right? So it will also
create trace one and span one or some
different span. Let's say span two.
Okay. Some unique spend, right? So this
is also create.
So that's what will happen when you will
use restline.create.
But when you use builder, it will add an
interceptor.
That interceptor will do in the header.
It will append this
trace parent where it has the trace ID
and the parent span ID. So that this
app2 will not create new trace. It will
use the same trace that yes, they all
part of same request. Even though it
will create a new span, but it will make
it that it's a its parent is S1.
It will add this info because in header
we have sent the trace id call hyphen is
span id. So this information we passed
and now its filter which filter server
http observation filter its filter will
catch it and it will append this
information.
Okay. So
for rest client this is important.
Similarly if you are using rest template
rest template is like you can say that
old way of invoking the API. So it will
this interceptor will not get appended
automatically. You have to use
observation rest template customizer.
Okay. So when you create a new rest
template object
and you have to in the customizer you
have to add this rest template object.
So what will happen is this interceptor
will start intercepting this rest
template
otherwise rest template also it will
this interceptor will not be present and
your app 2 will create a new trace.
Okay. So this header would be missing.
So if you are using rest template you
have to make sure that whenever you
create a new object of rest template you
need observation rest template
customizer and within this customizer
you need to add this rest template
object that's all. If you are using rest
template use builder one because
automatically spring boot will take care
of adding the interceptor but with this
create it will not add the interceptor
for faint line there is no need
automatically it would be handled but
please test it out. Okay. Uh,
automatically interceptor will get added
for the faint clients. But test it out
please.
Okay. So now we have done full setup.
We know that okay we our application one
is set up. Application two is set up.
Now when app um application one is also
invoking application two. We know that
how everything works is because of this
filters and interceptors. Now let's see
invoke an endpoint 80080 which is our
app 1. I am invoking / API endpoint
response from app 2 hello from app 2. So
this is coming from our app 2. So this
is what we change right response from
app 2 whatever the response we are
getting from app 2. So our app 2 is
returning hello from app 2. So means our
invocation is properly working.
Let's also see that. So here if you see
currently it's zero nothing. Let's also
refresh it. Currently Jagger all-in-one
this we can ignore. This is Jagger
internal something. So currently our
applications are not there.
This is our application trace
application one. I am starting this
application.
This is application two. I am starting
this application.
So application one is started on 8080.
Application 2 is started on 8082.
Okay. And application one controller it
has / API. Right? It is invoking rest
client. The same thing which we have
seen. Now let's hit that.
I am getting the proper response. Okay.
Now
let's goes to Jagger refresh it.
Trace F1 trace F_2 our application
comes. So goes to the F1.
So here if you see you can see the
trace.
Okay. So
if you click here you can see this
line. So you can see that
all this information u your application
one and then it invoked application two.
Let's understand this what info it is
showing.
So now when I hit it in the Jerger UI
you are able to see this when you in
when you see that app one right you will
see that okay you hit this endpoint and
this two microser involved. Now if you
go inside this so I when I go inside
this so let's go again back
here here I clicked here and I see trace
JSON okay you got the JSON so if you
notice the JSON
it has a trace ID let me zoom in a bit
it has a trace ID so here if you see
this is my trace ID and each and every
is spen has the same trace ID so means
these all span belong to a particular
trace
And this span is an array. So I have
given it a name like this is span one
span two span three. Three spans are
there total
now. So here first span trace ID is yeah
the same one which is there it is span
ID is this one. Operation name is / API.
So now understand with this one you have
an app one.
you have an app 2.
So now when the request entered the f1
incoming request it create a span. So
for incoming request a span is created.
Okay it has no parent. So currently yeah
no parent is there. Start time at this
time it is started and total time this
much it took. So when it finish this is
the total time it took.
Okay. So this is the process ID P1. This
is the process ID P1.
Now understand the span 2 trace id is
this only span id is new different. This
span id is for get making a http get
call. So from app one I am trying to
invoke app 2. So for outgoing call also
it create a new spin like this outgoing
to call take how much time? This is an
operation also. So this also a so that's
an ID for that operation unit of task
making an outgoing call and see this
reference
it's a child of this is a child this
span so let's say and this is returning
so this span got finished so this spen
is a child of this spen which is this
one
so it's a child of this one yeah because
see This this span
is the parent one. Then this is the
child.
Now focus on the span 3. Span 3 has a
dist trace ID same
some unique span id and operation name
is / ai/hello. So it's now this is its
incoming call / ai/hello. This its
incoming call. So a span is created for
this one.
So it's a child of 01 B it's this one.
So it's a child of this spin.
So at this time it is started this much
time it took and the process is P2. This
one is P2.
And here if you see this uh invocation
it process is P1. So means this is a
part of P1 only.
Okay. So all this information span has
multiple information. So this span
might
Jagger receive in not in order but with
this parent child information and with
this trace ID it can make this hierarchy
properly and using this hierarchy it can
construct this info.
Now here if you see we are seeing this
right
here we are seeing this lines. What this
line means? So again the same thing the
request entered the application. So this
is / API
it is entered and it is start doing some
work work work and at this point of time
another span create started for
invocation.
Okay. So invocation process is started.
Okay. At this point of time,
this is the new span which is like
service two trace two app two. Okay. So
this is like app two when it got invoked
and it finished and then after that uh
again call back to this app one. So so
this span is
total for invocation. So now you might
be thinking that hey Shri
app 2 has only worked for this much time
why invocation is taking this much time
right from see when we are invoking from
f_sub_1 is invoking app2
even app 2 works for only let's say 2
seconds but here it shows let's say
overall 5 second why because see there
is a network latency also network
latency time for serialization
So there are so many things happen. So
this is spend or this unit of task add
all those
time. This unit of task is only for how
much this app 2 has taken the time and
then the top one is like the overall
when the request enter and when it
finished.
Now you able to understand this
timeline.
Okay.
And yes, we can create manual span also.
So if you don't have to rely on just
input or you can say that incoming HTTP
uh this is outgoing HTTP request and
also this is nothing but an incoming
only
you you want that hey I am doing some DB
operation here. I also want to make sure
that how much time this operation has
take. So I want to create a span so that
I can uh have certain information. Yes,
we can create manual span also. Very
easy. So I told you that micrometer
expose certain endpoints. So tracer is
then interface. Okay. So this comes with
from an micrometer library. So we just
need to auto it. implementation comes
from the hotel uh open telemetry SDK
which we are using. Okay. So we need to
use this library and this is just uh for
testing purpose I am creating one
endpoint. Now the first important thing
is that
I am creating I am getting a current
span. So using this endpoint tracer dot
current spen what is the current spen
which is active. If there is no you
might get null. If there is any current
span you will get here. So this will act
as a parent for us. Okay. So here if you
see when I did this
I get this. Hey there is already a trace
ID.
Okay. See because when a request hits /
API/ test/ span it already created
because that's an incoming HTTP request.
So it already create one trace ID and
one span. Now I am internally trying to
create a new span, right? So there is
already a span. So that is the span ID
and that is the tracer ID. So we already
have one for the current span for the
incoming request.
Now I am creating a new spin. I am
creating tracer.next spen. Next spin
will create a new spin. Okay. And I pass
the parent span. If you don't pass the
parent span, it will do two things. It
will create a new trace ID and new span
ID. But if you pass the parent span, it
will reuse the trace ID, it will
generate a new span, but it will also
mark that hey, this is your parent span.
It has all this information.
Okay. So when you do next span and you
pass the parent span now the trace ID
would be this you will get a new span
but that new span would be a child of
this one and I gave certain name manual
child span whatever the uh span name you
want to give.
Now I have to start the span child span
dot start. Now very important part now
when you start it start the span only
timer will start that okay you are
starting the work now
but it will not set the current span as
this child span so what I'm trying to
say
current span
so let's say when HTTP incoming HTTP
request comes a New span is created and
that is set as current span. Now you are
creating a new span.
So this was a span one. Now you are
creating a span two. Even though both
have trace ID 1, trace ID 1 and the
parent here parent span is span one
only. So but this new span even though
you have started its timer is started
but it is not set as current span.
Current span is still your span one. So
let's say in future
when anywhere else you are try to fetch
the current span like this you will get
this parent one not the exact what you
have created okay so if your requirement
is that okay whatever the child span I
have created
if this is just for tracking the timing
I don't want to make it uh current span
Don't set this tracer dot with span
child span. Okay, if you don't want uh
to change the current span info but if
you want that yes whatever the span I
have created
internally possible that more span would
be created so that proper child relation
should come I need to you need to update
the current span because let's say when
you started a child task here when you
started the work and internally you are
creating another span
Internally also you are creating another
span and when it will try to do hey get
the current span what it will return
older one. So it would like hey this is
the child of this one no this is a child
of this span because within this it is
creating right right. So if you want a
proper hierarchy
update
so you can update it with like tracer
dot with span and pass the child span.
So this does two thing. So whatever the
object will return span in scope you
will see that it does two thing.
It has current it update the current
span information and it also maintain
old. So here if you see from start in
quick which one is the current span
trace ID is this and span ID is this.
This is for the incoming HTTP request.
incoming HTTP request.
Then after that we have created a new
child span. So when we created a new
child span so here if you see the trace
ID is used same because we have used the
parent span here but it created a
different span. So that's fine.
Now you started it and timer is started.
But I also wanted to update the current
span information. So when you did tracer
do with span and pass the child span. So
my current
span will become this one 137B1.
Okay. So here if you go inside this one
137B1 is my now current active span and
here it also maintain old context. Old
context would be your this one 64 its
parent
641.
Okay. Why? Why it maintain the current
and the old? Because now let's say your
child started now it's doing certain
work so I just use sleep 70 so that yes
certain work is done it takes certain
time and in finally I am closing this I
am closing the span in scope and I'm so
closing the child span so when you do
close this span in scope doc close what
it will do is it will pick the old
context and whatever the span it has it
will make it current Now, so you can say
that it reset it because this span is
closed. This child span is closed. Now,
which one is the active current span?
It's parent. So, its parent information
is present into the old context.
That's all.
Okay. So, that's all we have to do and
let's understand with demo. You got it
right. What we are doing is here there
is like
very basic thing but
we are all on same page and have right
information. So that's why I've written
so many things here so that when you
read it later things get clear to you.
So in one one minute I have the parent
span information. I created a child span
from the parent so that they have a same
trace. I started the child span. So it
timer got started and it timer get
stopped here when I'm closing it. So
timer stop.
Now I said the current
span is this one. But this also hold
information about the old like whatever
it span was going on.
Now once the task is completed we have
to close the span in scope. So once you
close it, it will this span is closed
right. So the current span need to be
updated right. So it will internally
update with the old context itself.
So that is done by this internally dot
close itself. We don't have to worry
about but we have to only make sure that
it is properly closed.
Okay? Otherwise your span even though
your span is finished your span is end
the current span is still not updated.
It will still show that current span is
this. So make sure that you properly
close the span in scope and the child
span also.
Okay. Now let's say that I have this in
the trace application one API 1
controller.
I have this SL API/ test SLS span the
same thing whatever I have told you take
out the parent span create a child spend
from the parent give it a name started
the timer
update the current span and just put
thread slip in the finally closing this
span so that uh the current span would
properly reset and after that I'm
stopping the timer. Okay. So, let's hit
it.
/ API slash this one. Let's hit that
response from F1. So, that's what it is
returning response from F1. Let's see
the Jagger.
So, here it goes now. So, here if you
see if I click here, so it created two
span. So this is for the parent one and
here if you see manual child span this
is what we created right manual child
span and if you see it's JSON
so this is the JSON information so spend
one span two this is an array trace ID
is the same for all so this is when the
incoming HTTP request for / API/ / test
/ span no child because this is the
first call no child no parent
this is the time it started this much
time it took when it might have gone so
this much time it took
now this is the span two
this is the same trace ID different span
and this is like manual child span so
that we are creating a new span within
this okay so it's a child of this span.
So it's a child of this span. So this is
the parent span. Internally we are
creating a new span. So this is a child.
So we have a proper information. So
parent span is this one
and this time it child spend start uh
start started when it finished. So
overall duration it took.
Got it? So simple right? So practice
with your hand.
uh refer the notes again things will get
clear to you but uh this is very
important because
when you would be learning about
distributed logging you will see that
logging is internally using trace ID and
trace ID concept is attached to
distributed tracing itself and this is
how distributed tracing works.
Okay guys let me know if there is any
doubt we can discuss further into the
comment section. Bye.